A Guide to the Nancy O'Brien Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Mayor of Charlottesville and City Council Member
  - C. Topical Files
    - 1976-1977 Economic Development Commission, 80 items (Box-folder 4:8)
      Included are newspaper clippings, by-laws of the Charlottesville-Albemarle Economic Development Commission, an annual report, a letter from Nancy O'Brien to Mitchell Van Yahres promoting the commission, a Chamber of Commerce Report, a list of Charlottesville businesses, a statement by Francis H. Fife, notes on a work session, and a position paper by Joseph W. Teague. Also included is information on the Heritage Land Company, Charlottesville Development Group, and condominiums on East Market Street. Correspondents include David W. Parrish, Jr. and Sandy Lambert
    - 1978-1979 Economic Development Commission, 29 items (Box-folder 4:9)
      There is a resolution by Cole Hendrix for a basic policy on economic development, a memo about Industrial Cost Recovery in Sewage Treatment, a list of proposals from the Schnitzel House, Michie Company, Rock Hill Academy, Vinegar Hill, McGuffey, and Starr Hill. There are printed copies of radio editorials about growth in Charlottesville and a symposium and discussion about economic development commissions for the city and the county.
    - 1973-1980 Economic Development Downtown Mall, 52 items (Box-folder 4:10)
      There are questions about the Downtown Mall from the Land use Committee of the League of Women Voters, a statement by Mayor Charles Barbour in favor of constructing the Downtown Mall, letters of protest about traffic being allowed on the mall, an ordinance for a special assessment for all property owners, a copy of the downtown assessment, a list of the property owners, itemized costs for the mall, guidelines for improvements in the mall by the University of Virginia School of Architecture, a resolution to extend the Downtown Mall, contract with Lawrence Halprin to finish the mall, petition for Monticello Hotel to be converted into condominiums, a list of the bids for completing the Downtown Mall and a resolution awarding the contract to R. E. Lee. Topics include land for Central Place on the mall, use of allocated funds from Vinegar Hill, definition of the Downtown Charlottesville, Incorporated, downtown bike race, Arts Education Festival, signage, lighting improvements, stage for Central place, usage for CSX property, and Leggett's Department Store leaving the downtown location.
    - 1973-1978 Economic Development Downtown Mall Newspaper clippings, 130 items (Box-folder 4:11)
      There are newspaper clippings about the work on the new downtown mall including its opening
    - 1976 Economic Development Farber Mall Constituents, 34 items (Box-folder 5:1)
      There are letters from constituents about the Fashion Square Mall. There is a resolution from the Greenbrier Neighborhood Association asking for the Planning Commission to undertake a study on water run-off and traffic issues; a memo outlining capital cost estimates and suggestions for sharing the cost between the city and the developer; an economic analysis and a traffic study report
    - 1977 Economic Development Farber Mall Constituents, 92 items (Box-folder 5:2)
      There are many letters from constituents and business owners to City Council about the mall proposal. (Included is a letter from Mrs. John Cooke Wyllie commenting on the changes in Charlottesville and her fears about going out at night alone; January 10, 1977.)
    - 1976-1977 Economic Development Farber Mall (City) Petyon Property, 49 items (Box-folder 5:3)
      There is an editorial from Francis Fife defending Nancy O'Brien in the controversy surrounding Leonard Farber's proposal for a shopping mall in the City of Charlottesville. There is correspondence from Leonard Farber and a press release describing a situation in which Farber did not want to pay the offsite costs for road improvements. There are memos from City Manager Cole Hendrix and recommendations from the Director of Planning and Development Satyrendra S. Huja. City Council passed the rezoning proposal for the mall. Meanwhile Farber had asked for a delay, and had presented the mall to the County. There are news clippings and reports about the mall idea moving to the County. (The mall was built on Rio Road and named Fashion Square Mall)
    - 1978 Economic Development Farber Mall (County), 10 items (Box-folder 5:4)
      There are letters about the mall being constructed on Rio Road in Albemarle County including a letter from Wallace Reed to the State Air Pollution Control Board about the potentially harmful effects of traffic and pollution from the mall; a radio editorial about roads that need to be built or improved for the mall; a letter from Nancy O'Brien to Gerald Fisher, Albemarle County Board of Supervisors, about her concerns for the proposed mall site; a Rich Collins letter to Nancy O'Brien about air pollution from increased traffic due to the mall; a letter from Bernard J. Haggerty to Nancy O'Brien accusing her of misrepresenting the majority vote for the mall and there is a letter from Nancy O'Brien to Haggerty defending her position and suggesting that he check his facts. There is also the official resolution adopted by the Charlottesville Albemarle Economic Development Commission to locate the mall in the community. (Louis Scribner)
    - 1976-1980 Economic Development Farber Mall Newspaper clippings, 130 items (Box-folder 5:5)
    - 1976 October-December Economic Development Farber Mall (City) Rezoning notebook, 1 notebook (Box-folder 5:6)
      Minutes of the Charlottesville City Planning Commission, applications and correspondence for rezoning of Fashion Square Mall
    - 1976 December 30- 1977 January 7 Economic Development Farber Mall (City) Rezoning notebook, 1 notebook (Box-folder 5:7)
      Minutes of a special meeting of the Charlottesville City Planning Commission on January 7, 1977 and correspondence regarding the Fashion Square Mall
    - 1976-1977 Economic Development Farber Mall (City) rezoning reports, 3 items (Box-folder 6:1)
      There are three reports, Impact Analysis on proposed commercial rezoning and stream relocation for mall, Correspondence about the mall which was received after the closing of the public record on January 10, 1977, and Rezoning Public Record
    - 1976-1977 Economic Development Farber Mall (City) Traffic reports, 7 items (Box-folder 6:2)
      There are two traffic impact analysis reports and related papers regarding the Farber Mall and the effects of the mall on the environment.
    - 1976-1977 Economic Development Farber Mall Work Sessions, 23 items (Box-folder 6:3)
    - 2004-2005 Economic Development Fifeville, 39 items (Box-folder 6:4)
      There is a proposal from Southern Development to purchase lots in Fifeville and Ridge Street (near Tonsler Park) and build apartments. There is extensive e-mail from Antoinette Rhoades about preserving the area for historic reasons. Dr. Charlie Hurt is also mentioned. There are also documents related to preservation of historic areas including a cd. There is a description of the history of Fifeville including information about Allen Hawkins and John Hartwell Cocke who were in business together.
    - 1974; 1978-1979 Economic Development McIntire Road Extension pt.1, 50 items (Box-folder 6:5)
      There is information from the North Downtown Residents Association, Starr Hill Neighborhood Association, City and County officials, design engineers and officials from the Virginia Department of Highways. There are study plans for an extension of McIntire Road with Rio Road. Also mentioned are improvements to Ridge Street, Cherry Avenue, McIntire Road, and Preston Avenue. There are also letters to Nancy O'Brien from constituents about McIntire Park.
    - 1980 Economic Development McIntire Road Extension pt.2, 21 items (Box-folder 6:6)
      There are constituent letters to Nancy O'Brien about McIntire Park; a McIntire Road Report by City Council, letters to Commonwealth Attorney Richard Barrick, City Attorney Roger Wiley, and Attorney General Marshall Coleman concerning an alleged conflict of Interest for Thomas Albro; City and County Resolutions approving the proposed extension, a Design Advisory Committee's Report to City Council, an opinion paper "North-South Route," recommendations by Wallace Reed, a report by Charles A. Kulp, letter from Don Wagner, Virginia Department of Highways and Transportation approving the report, and printed materials about McIntire Road and the Virginia Department Of Highways and Transportation
    - 1978-1980 Economic Development McIntire Road newspaper clippings, 39 items (Box-folder 6:7)
    - 2002 Economic Development Meadowcreek Parkway e-mails, 16 items (Box-folder 7:1)
      There are e-mails from Mary E. MacNeil, Bruce Appleyard, Rich Collins, John L. Pfaltz, John Dean, George Loper, and Kevin Lynch
    - 1974-1979 Economic Development newspaper clippings, 67 items (Box-folder 7:2)
      There are newspaper clippings about potential developments in Charlottesville and Albemarle County including revenues from the airport, proposal for a downtown seven story condominium, Miller and Rhoads relocating to Fashion Square Mall, widening of route 29, General Electric plant, Industrial Park near airport, Biscuit Run, Federal Executive Institute, sign regulations, and Dr. Hurt's illegal bridge over the South Rivanna River
    - 1978 Economic Development Vinegar Hill, 13 items (Box-folder 7:3)
      There is a resolution allowing that funds from the Charlottesville Development Group be used to complete an analysis of public costs for a Vinegar Hill Hotel and Conference Center; Correspondents include John W. Galbreath, Robert C. Stripling, Peter Kory, Mitchell Van Yahres, Robert L. Vickery, John B. Slidell of Zuchelli, Hunter & Associates, Inc. Included is a contract for consultant, Zuchelli, Hunter & Associates, Inc. to prepare a feasibility analysis for the City. Topics include a selection of a consultant for a market study and that the construction of a hotel downtown be a top priority of the Charlottesville Development Group. There are also news clippings
    - 1979-1980 Economic Development Vinegar Hill, 33 items (Box-folder 7:4)
      There is a resolution by the Charlottesville Development Group to have a downtown hotel and conference center, an announcement designating the construction to the Park-Tower Development Group of New York and correspondence about federal grants not coming through for the hotel. Also included is a report on Vinegar Hill Project Financial Costs and Benefits by Zuchelli, Hunter & Associates, Inc., a Vinegar Hill newsletter, a Starr Hill neighborhood letter requesting rehousing for the original Vinegar Hill residents, a letter discussing the inclusion of the YMCA in the hotel, a Vinegar Hill Impact Committee Report, a report by Scurlock Associates, Inc., and questions from the League of Women Voters.
    - 1978-1980; 1982 Economic Development Vinegar Hill History news clippings, 36 items (Box-folder 7:5)
      There are newspaper clippings showing how Vinegar Hill used to look before it was destroyed in 1960 for "urban renewal." There are also articles about the planned development of Vinegar Hill.
    - 1978 Economic Studies, 7 items (Box-folder 7:6)
      There are research papers by Hal Wolman and George A. Reigeluth from The Urban Institute about local economic development decision-making.
    - 1974-1978 Historical Landmarks in Virginia, 16 items (Box-folder 7:7)
      There is correspondence about a request for restoration of a building located at 609 East High Street. There is also a mission statement of the Virginia Historical Landmarks Commission, notes about the Levy Opera House, grant application for help with Midway Mill Restoration and various newspaper clippings about the Levy Opera House, Midway Mill, Charlottesville's First Street, Ivy property allegedly belonging to Thomas Jefferson, Paramount Theatre, Post Office and McIntire Library.
    - 1974-1984 Housing Issues, 57 items (Box-folder 7:8)
      There is a research paper on "Housing Issues and Strategies for Charlottesville" prepared by the Department of Community Development and many newspaper clippings (1974-1978). Included is a paper by Nancy O'Brien from her UVA class on Policy Analysis GFAG 866 in 1983.
    - 1976-1978 Invitations, 54 items (Box-folder 7:9)
      There are various programs and invitations to dinners, fundraisers, and events
    - 1979 Ivy Creek Natural Area, 1 item (Box-folder 7:10)
      There is a memo about a proposal for the revised master plan for Ivy Creek
    - 1974-1978 Lane High School, 15 items (Box-folder 7:11)
      There are newspaper clippings about the use of the Lane High School Building
    - 1972 Legislation, 6 items (Box-folder 7:12)
      There is correspondence to Mitchell Van Yahres from various senators regarding their support for Van Yahres opposition to Bill 328 which would place a moratorium on annexation in Virginia.
    - 1972-1979 Newspaper clippings on community service, 46 items (Box-folder 8:1)
      There are newspaper clippings about museums, libraries, law programs, UVA and other organizations that offer cultural experiences to the community.
    - 1974 Newspaper clippings on drug abuse, 8 items (Box-folder 8:2)
    - 1976 Newspaper clippings on elderly, 3 items (Box-folder 8:3)
    - 1975; 1978 Newspaper clippings on environment, 9 items (Box-folder 8:4)
    - 1977-1978 Newspaper clippings on labor, 18 items (Box-folder 8:5)
    - 1974 Newspaper clippings on landfill, 7 items (Box-folder 8:6)
    - 1971-1978 Newspaper clippings on land planning, 30 items (Box-folder 8:7)
    - 1976 Newspaper clippings on Charlottesville Mayors, 35 items (Box-folder 8:8)
    - 1972-1978 Newspaper clippings Miscellaneous, 12 items (Box-folder 8:9)
      There are articles about Asateague Island, the office of the Public Defender, government regulations, and business news
    - 1978 Newspaper clipping on Chic Moran, 1 item (Box-folder 8:10)
      There is an article on oral histories about the University of Virginia
    - 1975-1978 Newspaper clippings Police, 14 items (Box-folder 8:11)
      There are articles about DNA, crime rates, and salaries
    - 1974-1978 Newspaper clippings Pollution, 14 items (Box-folder 8:12)
      Topics include Morton Frozen Foods and phosphorus removal to protect the Rivanna River and Reservoir, waste in the Rappahannock River Basin, studies on the South Fork Rivanna Reservoir, and noise ordinances
    - 1974-1978 Newspaper clippings Prisons, 13 items (Box-folder 8:13)
      Topics include the creation of the Charlottesville Albemarle Regional Jail Board, programs to improve jail conditions, increased prisoner protection, study on work release program, alternatives to prison,
    - 1973-1978 Newspaper clippings Schools, 56 items (Box-folder 8:14)
      Topics include a discipline task force, school bus costs, budget cuts, salaries, shortening of elementary school day, quality of schools, Learning Exchange Program, and school improvements
    - 1974-1976 Newspaper clippings Sewer, 10 items (Box-folder 8:15)
      Topics include upgrading sewer treatment plants, sewer rates, suspension of Moores Creek Sewer Treatment Plant, and a "living filter" concept in Crozet
    - 1974-1978 Newspaper clippings Taxes, 33 items (Box-folder 8:16)
      Topics include tax reform, tax increases, cigarette tax, and Virginia Proposition 13.5
    - 1976; 1978 Newspaper clippings Tourism, 5 items (Box-folder 8:17)
      Topics mentioned are the Chamber of Commerce, Piedmont Airlines, and a new Visitor Bureau
    - 1974-1978 Newspaper clippings Transportation and Parking, 35 items (Box-folder 8:18)
      Topics mentioned are transit studies, bike paths, downtown parking, underground parking facility below Madison Bowl, taxi rate increases, bus rates, saving the Southern Crescent train, conditions of 29 North, and the resignation of the Charlottesville traffic engineer
    - 1971 Newspaper clippings Voting, 2 items (Box-folder 8:19)
      Topics included are the new voting process regulation of address registration and the Democratic Party meetings
    - 1976-1977; n. d. Ordinances, 33 items (Box-folder 8:20)
      Topics included are Constitution Highway Senate Joint Resolution No. 41; amendment to city code regarding group homes; budget appropriation for construction of taxi road at the airport, pedestrian mall, and visit to a sister city. There are ordinances about yard regulations, Blenheim Avenue, on-street parking, control of rainfall runoff, and anti-trust laws. There are also newspaper clippings about billboards, and new zoning ordinances.
    - 1976 Queen Elizabeth's Visit to Charlottesville, 14 items (Box-folder 8:21)
      There are newspaper clippings (University Register, The Cavalier Daily, The Daily Progress, and The Washington Post) about the visit, press statements, programs, a detailed itinerary, as well as printed instructions on how to address the Queen and other important members of the government. See also Scrapbook pages 1976 July (Box18)
    - 1976-1978; 2002 Race Issues, 20 items (Box-folder 8:22)
      There is a study of racial problems in the schools and Charlottesville, recommendations from the Social Development Commission, and an article, "Patterns of Black Excellence." There is also a program for a fashion show sponsored by the National Association of Advancement of Colored People. There are also newspaper clippings about racial issues including acts of violence against the Safeway Store
    - 2002 Race: Many Races, One Community, 75 items (Box-folder 9:1)
      There are newspaper clippings and statements from the police about a racial incident in Charlottesville where several high school students attacked University students. There are minutes, and reports from the group, Many Races, One Community which outlined a list of problems, a resolution of apology to the students, and outreach programs. The group was facilitated by Nancy O'Brien.
    - 2003 Race: Many Races, One Community, 39 items (Box-folder 9:2)
      There are lists of members of the group Many Races, One Community with e-mails, minutes and reports. Also included are brief histories of William Elwood, Drewary Brown, Robet H. Cooley III, Frances Brand, Sally Hemmings, Martha Jefferson, Lawrence Richardson, George Inge, Nannie Cox Jackson, Mollie Ingle Michie, Henry Martin, Sarah Patton Boyle, Anna Gardner, Rebecca McGinness, James T. S. Taylor, Rufus Holsinger, Uriah Levy, Nancy West, Carter G. Woodson, Edwin Anderson Alderman, Charles E. Coles, R.T. W. Duke Jr., Ben York, William Clark, Charles L. Barbour, Meriwether Lewis, Raymond Bel, Isaac and Simon Leterman, Ruth B. and George T. Huff, Dr. George Ferguson, Booker T. Reaves, Charles E. [Chic] Moran, Thomas Jefferson, Elizabeth Hemmings, J. J. Sylvester, Tucker Isaacs, Eli Howard, Sarah Ann Strickler, John West, T. J. Williams, Gregory H. Swanson, Monacan Indian George Whitewolf, Ellis Mopsik, and Alice Carlotta Jackson. The biographies were written by the Citizens for a United Community.
    - 2001-2002; n.d. Race: Resources, 8 items (Box-folder 9:3)
      Included is an article from the Washington Post Magazine, "The Lessons and Legacy of the Prince Edward School Closings" and articles from the National League of Cities about racial issues. There is also literature from the Focus Women's Resource Center titled, "Days of Dialogue 2002" and articles on "Conversation Cafes"
    - 2008-2009 Sister Cities, 25 items (Box-folder 9:4)
      There are newspaper clippings from The Daily Progress about the success of sister cities programs. Also included are proposals and guidelines for the program and by-laws.
    - 2001-2002 Transportation: Commonwealth Transportation Board, 50 items (Box-folder 9:5)
      Included is an application from Nancy O'Brien for the appointment to the Commonwealth Transportation Board; e-mails and letters of recommendation from Al Weed, R. Creigh Deeds, Katherine E. Slaughter and many others. There are also planning reports for highway construction and flyers about stopping the Route 29 Bypass.
    - n. d.; 1976-1978 University of Virginia, 14 items (Box-folder 9:6)
      Photocopy of a document written by Thomas Jefferson about the opening of the University of Virginia. There are also newspaper clippings about the University of Virginia regarding fraternities, Easters, better lighting, football star Billy Copeland, and experiments in solar energy
    - 1972-1978 Water South Rivanna Fork Articles and Reports, 90 items (Box-folder 9:7)
      Topics include marine growth in the reservoir, Moore's Creek Sewage Treatment Plant, moratorium on construction near the South Rivanna Fork due to pollution concerns, pollution from Morton Frozen Foods and farming near the basin, sewage interceptor line to Crozet, pollution studies, price increases for water, and an article on the history of water issues in Albemarle County since 1868. There are also some articles about the James River.
    - 1978; 1980; 2000 Water South Rivanna Fork Reports, 9 items (Box-folder 9:8)
      Included is a report to City Council, a request for 1979 funds, notes from a conference on water resource management and planning, a Watershed Management Plan, and assessment
    - 1975-1977; 1990-2000 Water Crisis, 75 items (Box-folder 9:9)
      There are newspaper clippings about a water shortage. Also included is a water shortage contingency plan, a declaration by Governor Mills E. Godwin, Jr. of a local emergency in the city of Charlottesville, memos from the Rivanna Water & Sewer Authority about conserving water, and ordinances to reduce water consumption. There are also letters from constituents and business owners regarding the water restrictions. There are minutes from the Charlottesville Albemarle Board of Realtors meeting on "Water Talk" in 2000 and reports on water demands from 1990 to 1999.
    - 1975-1978 Women, 33 items (Box-folder 9:10)
      There is statistical information about the numbers of women in politics, and minutes of a Citizens Task Force on Abused Women. There are also newspaper clippings on a variety of issues regarding women.
- Series II: UVA Classes
  - A. Graduate Student and Thesis
    - 1983-1985 UVA Admission letter, 14 items (Box-folder 10:1)
      There is a letter from the director of the Graduate Program in Public Administration advising Nancy O'Brien that she should take some social science classes since she did not have a bachelors degree. There is also a letter of acceptance for her to begin in the 1984 Spring term. Also included are her graduate record exam scores, transcripts from Massachusetts General Hospital School of Nursing, and grades from courses taken at the University of Virginia.
    - 1984-1985 UVA Assignments and Papers, 21 items (Box-folder 10:2)
      Included are tests and papers by Nancy O'Brien such as "The Exercise of Discretion in Police Service," "Citizen Participation in School Systems," "Ethnography of the Charlottesville Democratic Party City Council Campaign Committee," " Effect of '85 Budget on Subsidized Housing, A Theory on the Effect of Registration Drives on Voter Turnout," "Analyzing Alternative Delivery Systems," "Stare Decisis," and "The Executive."
    - 1983-1985 Thesis notes on Planning District Commissions in Virginia, 35 items (Box-folder 10:3)
      Included is a study on Planning District Commissions in Virginia; title, and a publication, "Virginia Planning, Housing & Districting Legislation 1973." There is also a list of city codes and legislative acts; notes on Stanley Kidwell and Virginia Planning Commissions, Weldon Cooper Center for Public Service, and William Shelton (interview)
    - 1985 Thesis notes on Planning District Commissions in Virginia, 18 items (Box-folder 10:4)